we have seen a glimpse of fully
associative caches so now let's go from
the other direction which is let's first
look at direct mat caches if this is the
memory and it contains blocks 0 1 2 3 4
5 6 Etc and these are the block numbers
not the addresses so I'm assuming that
this thing here is an entire block worth
of memory which contains multiple
locations and let's say we have a cache
with room for four blocks we canot
number the lines 0 1 2 and three and in
a direct map cache block zero if it's in
the cach at all needs to be in line
number zero block one if it's in the
cach at all will be in slot number one
block number two if it is in the cache
at all has to be in this place here
block number three if it is in the cash
at all has to be here and now block
number four will again get to map to
line number zero block number five maps
to line number one block number six maps
to line number two Etc so pretty much
for any given block address there is
only one place in the cache where that
address can be if we look at a memory
address the least significant bits are
still the block offset they tell us
where in the block are we assuming that
we find the block the block number now
contains some bits that tell us where in
the cache this block can be the index
bits need to be sufficient to tell us
which of the lines in the cache are we
talking about so if there are four lines
in the cache then we need two index bits
to tell us where a block can map and
that is why in the block
number it was 0 1 2 3 0 1 2 3 Etc it was
determined by the lowermost bits of the
block number and the remaining bits of
the the address are now the tag now
there is an interesting question of why
the tag does not include the full block
number so why doesn't the tag cover also
the index bits and the answer to this is
that the tag needs to tell us which of
the blocks do we have in this place and
the answer is that the tag needs to
identify which block we have in the
cache considering that the block with
some index bits has to be in one place
in the cache the tag for that place in
the cache doesn't need to tell us what
the index bits are by looking at this
particular line we have already
determined that these index bits have to
be the ones that correspond to that line
so all we have to do is tell us which of
the lines that can possibly be here do
we really have and for that we only need
these bits because the index bits are
pretty much predetermined once we are
already looking here in other words if
we stored the index bits in the tag all
of the tags that we could possibly put
here would have the same index bits
which means we don't have to store them
because we already know them